<manpage id="tnc" cat="cmd" title="tnc">
  <namesection>
    <name>tnc</name>
    <desc>tnc is an expat parser object extension, that validates the XML
stream according the document DTD while parsing.</desc>
  </namesection>
  
  <synopsis>
    <syntax>package require tdom
package require tnc

set parser [expat]

tnc $parser enable</syntax>
  </synopsis>

  <section>
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    
    <p><m>tnc</m> adds the C handler set &quot;tnc&quot; to an tcl expat parser
obj. This handler set is a simple DTD validator. If the validator detects the
first validation error, it sets the interp result, signals error and stops
parsing. There isn't any validation error recovering. As a consequence, only
valid documents are completely parsed.</p>

    <p>This handler set has only two methods:</p>

    <commandlist>
      <commanddef>
        <command><cmd>tnc</cmd> <m>parserObj</m> <method>enable</method></command>

        <desc><p>Adds the tnc C handler set to a Tcl expat parser object.</p></desc>
      </commanddef>

      <commanddef>
        <command><cmd>tnc</cmd> <m>parserObj</m> <method>remove</method></command>

        <desc></desc>
      </commanddef>
    </commandlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>BUGS</title>

    <p>The validation error reports could be much more informative and
user-friendly.</p>

    <p>The validator doesn't detect ambiguous content models (see XML
recomendation Section 3.2.1 and Appendix E). Most Java validators also doesn't,
but handle such content models right anyhow. Tnc does not; if your DTD has
such ambiguous content models, tnc can not used to validate documents against
such (not completely XML spec compliant) DTDs.</p>

    <p>You cannot validate XML documents with standalone="yes" in the XML
Declaration</p>

    <p>Violations of the validity constraints Proper Group/PE Nesting and
Proper Conditional Section/PE Nesting are not detected. The could only happen
inside a invalid DTD, not in the content of a document.</p>

  </section>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Validation</keyword>
  </keywords>
  
</manpage>






